let me just type this in the chat all
right so how do I pronounce your name
matheus may see us now - she's fine
matheus okay have you been to any have
you been to one of these before do you
know how these work yes okay I mean it's
just basically a structured conversation
but yeah so we're just going live in one
oh we are live we are live already sorry
had anything okay so yeah so this this
solution raising is on game B which is
deliberately slightly vague right so it
leaves the space very open for a what
your interpretation of game B might be
and secondly how we might move towards
it so there's three sections of it the
first one is what are we doing right now
the second section is what would your
perfect version of it look like and then
the third and final part which is the
longest bit is sort of the adjacent
possible how might we move from where we
are towards what might be better you
know what I mean how can we take a step
on the road towards it
and so yeah I mean anyone can go
whenever they want to really we don't
need to go around in order doesn't need
to be that rigid so if anyone's got
anything they want to kick off with then
go ahead I've got some stuff so I really
just immerse myself in everything in
kind of the game B universe mostly
through Jordan Hall and Daniel smacking
burger and you know some others as well
I'm just kind of starting I got really
inspired still and feeling inspired
started writing kind
science fiction maybe fantasy book of
that would be the game B universe in the
future and then the history basically
you know the war or the civilizational
collapse at least partial or whatever
you know that's not really outlined yet
I'm kind of on chapter 1 but it would it
would go back in time also and then show
you you know kind of what happened and
then you know the stages of chaos that
kind of ensued until game B finally came
into being I'm a little bit stuck and I
actually messaged Jordan Paul I don't
know if he'll respond he's probably
pretty busy but I messaged him through
of all things LinkedIn because that was
like the first email spot and I only
have 300 characters to ask him a
question
but basically where I'm a little bit
stuck is that you know there are these
elements when you listen to you know in
particular like the the the I'm sorry
like the YouTube video of Jamie wheel
and Daniel and Jordan all speaking and
it's like a two-hour maybe three hour
conversation and they are attempting to
kind of have that third other that comes
up in a in a really good conversation
you know the the coach getting the
coherence and then having that emergent
property of something new coming up from
all those three elements coming together
and then forming something new so I kind
of asked them that in kind of I asked
him basically you know in trying to
define what at least their current
vision was is this you know I'm not
going to call it magic but like fantasy
is basically when you look at fantasy it
involves magic something magical happens
when you look at science fiction it's
some kind of technological thing that
happens in general so I kind of see the
game be needing a little bit of both and
I'm not saying that there's something
necessarily matte well going on about
this emergent property of something new
arising
from three people communicating but I'm
also seeing that as potentially maybe
not quite being enough to create a game
be if that makes sense yeah so if I met
yourself if I'm a you're saying can I
jump in cuz I've got it I've got a
couple of things which may help clarify
for you
so first of all Jordan has embarked on
something concrete now called the sybian
project I don't know they're just last
week or something yeah which is which is
exactly that I think an attempt to fuse
you know the the magic and the grounded
actual working in the real-world
elements and secondly what your points
into is also kind of a repetitive
problem in the problem made is not the
right word but conflict should we say in
the game be space between those who
think that it's about primarily personal
development and making good people and
those who think is primarily about
systems design you know what I mean and
there and there's always been a certain
amount of friction between those two
things and so what you said about both
are required is absolutely necessary I
think if I if I could just try to get us
to broadly focus in the first section on
what we are doing now rights of what it
is you know sort of character particular
characteristics of game a that that we
would like to see change as individuals
right you know I mean that that kind of
things I'm sure we've all got all got
our stuff mm-hmm the military point of
it problems you know or sale
environmental destruction those are
probably my three top ones yeah I've
gotta say what I like about the game be
thing is is how war and environmental
destruction and they all actually come
under the saying it's all the same
dynamic right it's all it's all this
rivalry sness you know what I mean is is
it's that which is the central time
which is what I has really appealed to
me is that zoom out and you know but
understanding that all of these problems
are actually the same thing playing out
in different domains right sorry I've
already spoken too much and kerri-anne
Macias having a chatter to say anything
yet so I'll shut up now sorry I'll let
you go okay so um
trying to find the shortest possible
description of game a comes to mind as
to things really well as scarcity and we
are being regulars because there is some
scarcity and there will always be
because of example one Mona Lisa right
so things like resources resources food
and the bottom of mussels pyramid they
do not need to be scarce we can actually
we don't have now means to make all this
physical scarcity go away basically and
the scarcity is the basis of they may
because also the second second thing
about Lynn is that it is a game and it
operates on one principle only which is
profit anything and everything that is
gained I it all comes to one simple
question does it bring money if it
doesn't it's worse if it generates
profit it's good and I think fine and on
this basis we are the world is now in
the state this yeah one thing I remember
I mean I felt this for super long and
I've gotten into little arguments I have
you know some conservative friends and
you know I've spent a lot of time trying
to understand the conservative viewpoint
you know and now to the point where it's
like it doesn't trigger me because I
understand kind of some of the
fundamental beliefs which are really
good and of which you know even like the
idea of sovereignty and and personal
responsibility our conservative
perspectives that's like the are the
fundamentals and those are actually
really key elements of a successful game
be so in a lot of ways they could speak
well to the game be world
that being said you know things like
shorting stocks where you make them you
make your money when someone else fails
is something that I've for years have
said that's just not how things should
work like it's one thing in sports you
know somebody loses you know and you're
rooting for them to lose but um you know
when it really comes down to people's
lives and ability to get by that is just
a crime so it was so that's what kind of
blew my mind once I really started
understanding what people were talking
about in that some of these like
Breville wisdom is kind of how I came
across all these folks and it actually
took me months to even realize there was
something called game B I was just
listening to them going wow these people
are really smart and these are
interesting subjects and then yeah
anyway you know and with the stocks it's
not it's it again it would be one thing
if you've lost faith in a company in
which you hold stock and you choose to
sell you're holding in them as opposed
to taking a pump on them failing in the
future not even actually having any
stock to sell right but promising to buy
stock in a in the future for less money
that yeah yeah I mean it's and what it
does is also it puts pressure on the
company through no fault of their own
you know now all of a sudden their share
price is under pressure because people
are shorting them through nothing that's
actually going on in the business you
know so yeah no I completely agree with
that all about you Carrie well basically
I think every yeah well game a as I said
I agree with everything that you said
and about profit and it's not about
human beings anymore not about enough
what's what's kind of been missing
everyone who's talking about everyone's
written realities on all its black
shirts and it's about and those
structures are causing of even more the
motivations as well go in and
everybody's living in a state of fear
now where they don't even trust anyone
so gameid there's no trust there anymore
there's no nothing and nobody's willing
to unless there's pounds attached to it
so it's fine then I think well obviously
at the worth oh it's too much just now
because I've got an idea of how to and
things are being bubbling underneath
the service but nobody's willing to
reach out to anybody anymore or even
have a conversation or a chat you know I
mean so that's the actual um so I'd say
it was them there's no care in-game a
there's no cure at all there's no only
notice there's no transparency there's
no let's see what we can try and there's
no willingness
well there is willingness and there's
people in different silos it was all
like calling for all trust and
everything yeah but that's in spite all
problem because with everything to do it
what do you know you know I mean massive
thinking that you've spent some time
around the Venus Project and
resource-based economics I'm just from
some of the language that you used it
sounded quite yeah I mean I started
looking into alternatives to live a long
time ago and came across like many
products and the Venus yeah I have
friends in Polish chapter of of this
organization we are thinking about and
do some resource sharing and yeah try to
introduce new economy in in some small
form so we see yes the resource-based
economy is what I would like to see in
the future it just makes sense right
there's finite and other resources they
need to be recycled we can build
beautiful things upon materials recycled
from the previous and obviously mmm
unless we are thinking about mining
asteroids and bringing resources down
from the space just you know there's no
other way really to get this production
consumption under control there just the
notion of sharing rather than owning
you're removing the notion of ownership
and
notion of the requirement to make profit
from everything that you do just those
two things alone
makes a massive difference to resource
demand you know what I mean IIIi mean
the massive yep so there is one thing
that came to mind just moment ago I
don't understand why there is this split
between advancement in technology and
self improvement as humans I mean there
was some it obviously needs to be both
right yeah we have technology it just
needs to be perfect it and brought to
the white public I'd say for free but
it's you don't really and then it's also
kind of obvious I know I know to me that
we as humans have some homework to do as
well and this is also what I found in
fragments in The Venus Project there was
something about that there and at the
meaning crisis obviously and some kind
of psychology cognitive science and and
yeah religion and magic as well so it
seems clear that humans as we are now
without meditating without like
self-examination and you know getting
deeper into what motivates us and we
have growing spirituality and I'm not
saying any kind of whoo yeah yeah
three girls people that whoo you've just
hit on you've just hit on exactly what
the problem was could be because you're
right so any intelligent person clearly
it's both you can make design the best
systems in the world if they're
populated by corrupt people they're soon
gonna collapse in on themselves right
and similarly you can have the loveliest
people in the world without decent
systems to coordinate nothing ever gets
done so I mean you know it is obvious
however the whoo thing is exactly what's
caused the schism because
those who advocate the greater emphasis
being on personal yeah not to the
exclusion of systems but the main
emphasis should be on personal
development the accusation leveled
against them is that that's all a bit
whew and you know what I mean not
everyone's into the whole spiritual
thing and bla bla bla bla bla and this
has to be a vocabulary that talks to
everyone and yeah it's it's a difficult
one it's a difficult one I mean I'm
certainly no goddess but I do believe
that a commitment to something beyond
yourself right the the the the
understanding that there is a bigger
game than just your life going on here
and that you're inspected however you
conceptualize that right but but there
is something bigger than you going on
here
I do think an understanding or a
recognition of that is is deeply
important yep yeah the thingis is the
key and I guess that triggers people
about it being Oh as in something
negative its if we ascribe to many weird
adjectives to the bigger because the
bigger is someone might say the bigger
thing is like universe being conscious
and gods and everything and all the
unnecessary projections of how we think
the bigger thing what it is we have
really no chance to describe it properly
because we are limited in our capacity
to define things that same for everybody
this genuinely is not the same for
everybody right so you know there has to
be freedom for everyone to have their
own thing the the but I think what is
common to all of us is that we need that
that bigger context in which to place
ourselves right we all need that so you
know it's like I don't feel familiar
with non-violent communication but I
think it applies across all kinds of
domains right and it's about this
distinction between needs and strategies
is really
really important that you understand
that and so this this maps very well so
that right the need the psychological
need we all have is to be part of is to
understand that we're part of something
bigger than that right but the
strategies that we use to satisfy that
need is different for all of us for some
of its religion for some community for
some of its its nature
whatever it might be you know I mean it
really doesn't matter what it is the
point is to recognize that we are all
attempting to meet that same need being
sensitive to the fact that different
people meet that need in different ways
right and and and once once you're there
once you understand that we're all
actually all on the same thing we're all
trying to do the same thing we're just
going about it in different ways if you
can actually really deeply understand
that then conflict becomes not a thing
to get angry over and fight over it
becomes a space in which to generate new
ideas right the the clash of difference
is now a generative thing right it's not
it's not it's not destructive its
generative and so that that records for
me this is the deep deep deep thing of
game be is that recognition that we are
all on the same team we might have
completely different ideas about things
but despite that we are still on the
same team and we never ever lose sight
of that yeah we only we all shit we all
sleep do you know what I mean and
they're there there's and that's what
everything is built on everything else
is built on that a few minutes and
although the problem assaults yeah well
so let's just add the the idea of
coherence in a bit so you know obviously
there's a lot of effort on governments
you know United States government in
particular it feels like does a lot of
you know you call it propaganda or you
know with trying to get everybody on the
same page and there's not a lot of real
trust in what is being spread through
mainstream media and the leadership in
general and there's clearly some type of
battle going on between you know the
blue church and the red religion or
basically you know the the Heeia
establishment and Donald Trump it's a
pretty scary time to be over here in a
lot of ways
so a couple of things which are you know
kind of these mean plexes self-enforcing
idea structures that further polarize
people that are problematic within the
universe so anyway you know like
Christianity's thing of that if you
don't believe you know that's the devil
talking in your ear and therefore you
will burn in hell is such a powerful
enforcer of a belief system which
divides you from people who are
unbelievers so it's really challenging
to work with that and there's some
similarities and some of the Islamic
faith as well and so you know it's
really hard to get
find that inner coherence when there are
people that are literally protecting
themselves from joining you that be with
every single person on the planet right
this is this is a really important thing
so yeah yeah you know you find your
people and that doesn't mean that you're
a bigger right it means that you find
your people we are people in the world
that we can talk to some of them agree
with us saw them don't disagree with but
we can talk to them right we can have a
reasonable conversation with and if you
you know if you can counsel people that
you simply calm or it's gonna take way
too much effort before then you just
don't you know what I mean do their
thing you can't build bridges with all
people it's just impossible so so the
the idea that I'm kind of getting around
to is just like the body has numerous
independent systems that all function
together create an entire you know
perhaps it's okay that we you know like
not it's not up to me anyway but you
know perhaps it's okay to have you know
the Islamic faith and the Christian
faith doing its own thing of course not
they're gonna literally go to war with
each other that's a that's a separate
issue but
you know so you look at like I'm a big
fan longtime fan of Ken Wilber integral
theory and these stages of development
and I do think so you know he thinks
that we're at approximately maybe 3% of
integral thinkers you know I'm not sure
if you say a world or in this country
but like people who have the ability to
see all of these different partial
truths and be able to integrate them all
into you know a more coherent view of
what's going on in the world and so
that's a step above post-modernism and
these more kind of like somewhat
divisive belief systems below it so I
think that the goal for game B is to get
that number up to 10% which is the
theoretical tipping point for Humanity
to start working together and coherence
again so you know I think everything
that we can do as individuals and
collectively to start thinking on the
integral side of things and then
spreading that viewpoint in whatever
ways is you know it's gonna kind of get
a get us to that 10% but we're in a race
spreading viewpoints is something that
troubles me it really does if you point
so that it feels mission it feels
missionary like you know what I mean it
feels different to the Christian
missionaries going around telling all
the natives that they had to go there
Jesus it feels no different
that's why I mean that's why I'm writing
we feel it's more enlightened philosophy
does not mean that we have to go around
spreading it if it's good it spreads on
its own just let's talk about Star Trek
Star Trek was kind of the foundational
elements of
post-modernism where like you know they
have numerous races that they're you
know alien races and they are all
working together and they functionally
didn't you know they never really went
to war so that was that viewpoint so by
creating stories whether it's myths or
whatever or sharing your ideas about
kind of that tear true integral theory
of pulling all of these partial truths
together is it's a good idea I'm not
saying you create propaganda manipulate
I mean it's
propaganda with no matter how you look
at it there's an internal or not you've
got to get people on the same page I
mean that's just how that's what
coherence is so you know you can look at
it as some dark force I mean I've
sometimes wondered of like maybe there's
maybe the blue church and stuff actually
has our best interest in the heart but
it's just so fucking hard to see it and
trust them on some level that you know
we demonize it but anyway I think that
tier 2 aspect of you know Ken Wilbur's
integral thought though is you know but
been the wit the filter that I'm kind of
looking at thing though yet but I'm
looking at things through so the notion
of drawing together strands of truths
from lots of different places and
synthesizing them into into something
that you know works and and is adaptive
to you into the world and so on it's not
it's not I mean to an extent we all do
that you know all the time in our lives
right I mean it all he's done is kind of
codify something that we all do anyway
and yeah I mean integral theory I'm not
deeply familiar with it I have some
familiarity with it and it's it's very
good and it has decent explanatory power
what I find with it well not so much
with it but with many of the people that
get really into it is that they to cut
on the Mac so beautiful and so appealing
that they kind of get lost in the map
and they forget that the map is just a
map right is not actually the territory
and the whole point of a map is to
inform your actual life and make it more
manageable and better and more enriching
and all of that kind of thing and and
not to get lost in the map and it seems
I mean it is as I say I'm not deeply
familiar with it and it is it is a good
map but I'm my encounters with people
who have got deeply into it it made me
somewhat resistant there's a certain
zealotry that seems to come along with
it right and that's that's that's made
me a little bit hesitant to get deeply
into it I don't know if you encountered
the same thing well it's interesting yes
yes and he literally stalks about the
map and the territory ken does you know
and and I've you know I've moved away
from it on in a general sense because
like you know no I don't
want to pay $500 for your sharp you know
slick-looking marketing campaign to take
classes about it but you know when I
started really getting involved in game
be it it came up in my consciousness on
its own after years of not really
reading can even though I've read you
know majority of his books where I just
went oh you know this really fits into
kind of what Ken's been talking about
which is like you know patterns like
there you know there really is different
stratifications like you know white
nationalism or nationalism is you know
as in Ken Ken's words like an orange
level way of viewing the world and
post-modernism which is a more liberal
viewpoint is the green level looking at
the world and they both have correct
aspects we do want to you know like
tribes are good and important you know
we're a tribe here right now we're game
B tribe you know but that doesn't mean
we're the most important thing you know
what I mean so anyway but I hear you on
just coming up to the half-hour mark
which is where the adjacent possible
begins and so I mean we heard that it's
my fault entirely we've kind of drifted
off and just had a conversation which is
fine but before we get into the sort of
adjacent possible bit can we just go
around quickly and everyone summarized
walks you know the perfect game B world
looks like yeah what is it what are we
actually trying to get to as best as you
can articulate and I get it may be
somewhat fuzzy but as best you can
you know what what does the game be
world look like it's done we're there
transition is done complete we're there
where we're playing game B what does it
look like okay Solar Punk which is all
this mix of Technology and green stuff
like trees and villages and small units
look at the big cities you can but it's
all beautifully matched when if the
nature so this is something I would
really like to see
as opposed you know the concrete and
steel and everything we are part of
nature and our technology is part of
nature as well so the best thing would
be for them to come together and mix in
a artful way
so that's externally and internally
because the post-transition
we all have resources and we don't have
to worry about food and anything else
basically for the survival for existence
we struggle with jobs or anything
everything's automated so what we are
free to do is basically anything and for
me it would include I've been able to
learn everything other languages playing
instruments and talking to people and
yeah meaningful relationships with
everyone and yeah lack of fear it's the
most beautiful thing about openness
vision yeah I am I agree with all of
your sentiments and you know I think
those the small communities I camera
brought the name of it is there's some
like upper number done by a number maybe
communities of no more than 150 people
where you know in terms of
responsibility you talked about freedom
to do anything you know I think there's
with that where's that freedom is also
the responsibility of working in
coherence with at least you're under the
50 person hub and perhaps there's weekly
or monthly get-togethers where maybe
you're all connected to the internet and
you know and sharing with other local
hubs you know any major decisions or
changes in your local community I'm not
really sure exactly
you know I'm kind of fleshing this out
in my own little sci-fi story of how you
know you work in harmony with the
surrounding hubs too so and then how
that might collectively happen to some
degree across the planet so it's almost
like there's a represent there's a
representative for every you know ten
thousand people or something that's
supposed to represent you on a
democratic thing maybe it's just broken
up into smaller things and that creates
you know like that antifragility is
created by more networks like the way
mycelium works mycelial networks it's
all interconnected so we just need you
know more involvement and more
interconnectedness going on throughout
the system to make it more anti fragile
and so yes that includes breaking down
you know the fear of other and the
connection and the shared humanity and
those kind of pieces to kind of keep us
you know that's our responsibility along
with our freedom you know everyone on
the planet and we care of self care of
others care the place and care the
planet and I think once that's achieved
and people actually all the divisions
and the fractures have been glued
together and people get to know who
everybody is and now and just and then
the global what happens all the
collective intelligence its global right
now with it with all the stuff that's
going on and the technology is actually
harness in a way that will feed back
into the local and the individual that's
what I was like to see and I do have
ideas about that yeah you've pretty much
said it all haven't you it's interesting
that both Yossarian and Mathias you came
up with this idea of like this whole
onic thing right so you've got
connections within connections within
connections and I think I think that is
it everyone seems to home in on
something along those lines right this
interconnectedness this complex web of
interconnections is what sustains feeds
develops protects you know what I mean
it does it does all of those things and
so yeah what we are doing right now this
is the this is the spores this is the
seeds of Gabey right again in the
formation of these relationships and
connections with each other and the the
Dunbar thing for me anyway you mentioned
is specifically Assyrian it's something
I've been on for a long time there and
that this works in a fractal
multi-dimensional way right and so you
know you've got you 150 people or
whatever let's say 100 for the sake of
argument cuz 100 hundreds is ten
thousand right scales really nicely but
you've got your hundred people that you
live with and you rely on each other for
you know food and cleaning the water and
and and dealing with the waste and blah
blah blah blah blah is that these
communities are largely self-sustaining
only maybe not a hundred percent but
largely self-reliant self-sustaining and
that members of that community are also
in communities of a hundred with people
who are another community so they can
collaborate on things that affect more
than just their own local community and
and that these things are virtually
infinite in number right you create a
massive amount of connection complexity
and so to give you it gives you the
opportunity to collaborate across any
relevant scale right so if you're
building a road then this you know this
set of communities is involved in that
and are going to benefit from it and are
gonna do most of the work on it and
whatever but if you're building I don't
know
transcontinental underground train
Network right then everyone's involved
in this and so the ability to have these
collaborations haven't had whatever
scale is needed while still affording
the communities the ability to live
exactly how they want to fucking live
worship what they want to worship
celebrate with on a celebration you know
what I mean with
anyone getting in their way over there
and still be able to collaborate on
stuff that is going to benefit everybody
with people who have totally different
belief systems and ways of life for the
way they do but but but nevertheless we
can collaborate on this thing right
because we're safe and succumbing that
that notion of safety I get that was
UMass this wasn't it talking about
safety that notion of being safe is so
important not what not worrying about
waiting away or next meal is coming from
how you're gonna get to work the next
morning you know whether you're whether
your family is going to be ok when you
go on holiday for a couple weeks all of
this kind of thing just that sense of
just absolute safety right that people
are out there to look after you and help
you out when you need it and not to try
and get shit off you when they can and
get one over on you and they all
environment anyway how can we get there
I'll shut up now sorry I talk for way
longer than I intended so I've got a bit
the head of steam up and going but
what's a thing a thing we could actually
do now we didn't diamond Jubilees
general framework is 10,000 people
hundred thousand dollars you know what I
mean that kind of scale assuming that
you could get 10,000 people and how each
paying $10 into a kitty to do something
actual in the world to move us towards
there what do you what what sort of
things can you see about like stuff and
how to create this and I think
collaboration tools freely accessible
collaboration tools and building
something that can you use across the
platforms that you can actually because
as I said you start with a conversation
and then that idea goes somewhere and
when you're stuck then behind so like
payroll and collaboration tools with us
you know a lot of the time you don't
have the Meletis or like paid up with
those groups that want to do something
and it's not about the money but you
just want access to the tools so I think
that would be a Kickstarter and as I
said they've got ideas to talk to
Matthew about saris which drops I know I
said I was gonna shut up oh I know a
woman in Australia who has created a
platform for exactly this purpose to
collaborate with other people on
projects it's specifically I will put
you two in touch with each other it is
dead mice Carrie Carrie Stedman her name
is
I'm sorry Carly no Carrie Kylie Kylie
steppin I have created my own obviously
because everyone seems to be creating
their own projects which is cool not the
best use of resources obviously but uh
yeah it's Kalei sorry to say instead
kyl ie and then step in its ste a DM aen
she's on Facebook you can find her in
the game you can find it through game be
on Facebook otherwise I'll sent oh I'm
on the wrong computer but I'll find her
email I'll find her email or something I
said it I don't fuck or email I talked
to a three messenger I don't even know
if I've got her email but I'm seeing
it's know I'm in a conversation with the
later on tonight so I'll tell her I'll
tell her to expect a message from you
just send her a thing on messenger and
also has to expects one from you so she
doesn't think it's spam okay so yeah
there's this thing already happening as
you mentioned that you know we're
already doing the little nodes right
here and so we want to get to 10,000
people - you know maybe we want to
create like a visual like a visual and
written or maybe video guide to what
this looks like the game be universe
looks like and we want to poll everybody
that's kind of interested in game being
some measure of coherence like agreement
that this is the rough outlines of what
the EMB universe looks like maybe if we
could you know there's hundreds I don't
know how many people are joining game be
every week I'm certainly trying to
spread the idea as much as possible
myself right now we could you know we
can't have a meeting with with 10,000
people we can't have a meeting with a
hundred people we actually need to have
it probably no larger than ten to kind
of be able to get an idea out there and
people ask questions to kind of get all
on the same page so maybe we're doing
you know little groups of ten and then
one person from that group is maybe
going to the next group or something to
kind of well let's say there's a there's
a concept called open space have you
heard of this because this is really
well because it does the mixing for you
automatically and it curates the system
for you automatically as well you know
the bad faith players soon get left
alone in rooms right and the damage that
bad faith players can cause is limited
naturally by by people's freedom to move
from room to room right so you know you
can have a hundred people and you break
them into say 25 rooms of for each right
and at any given time anyone can up and
leave the room and they go into a
waiting room and that once there's four
in a way soon and that becomes another
room right and so it naturally mixes and
circulates people and people pick up
ideas in one room which then disseminate
to another room and if an idea gains
traction in the general space right then
it will emerge the idea is that the
really good stuff emerges from because
everyone's talking about it by the end
everyone's yeah yeah yeah this is a
really good idea and that okay okay very
cool people I've done it with 16 I've
not tried with anything larger than that
but it is a very good thing about a open
space meetings in Chicago I'm not them
for the one elf with lots of people and
place out dreams and that is absolutely
brilliant it was I mean you learn so
much from other people and you pick up
ideas and it's absolutely excellent but
not so me online and I was I am I was a
well to unity week it's been going on so
I've been watching some of the
presentations and stuff this has been
some excellent stuff that's been coming
out of that you know I mean so asked one
one of them a question and the answers
are not it was really good so when and
yeah some of its in the moon of this but
I'm it's it's you know the people who
care people who care even occurred in
the universe or whatever side they're on
the gay you know so it's about
connecting all the people who actually
do care together and then from there on
just by turning out you've demonstrated
that you give a shit right
so you're with me by virtue of the fact
they've turned up they've made the
effort to turn up yeah absolutely
absolutely mm-hmm of talking to Mattias
Matus on them stuff and I've got I've
got ideas but the no to be honest I
can't articulate them just yet because
it will just come out in the garbled Mir
yeah I think I think I've said to you
before Kari that the axe but even if you
don't show what you've written down to
anybody it doesn't matter just just the
forcing yourself through the discipline
of writing it down step by step just
just clarify think come up with your
life but I just said it it's all kind of
still I'm still falling across that the
people are not so it's you know I mean
so and you know what I'm like Hello I
told the legs off don't please I try not
to do that just now so how does this
I mean how quickly would this open space
take to bring up you know all the facets
of game be that we were just talking
about and have a bland before the it
takes as long as it takes right senses
reach in an hour it may take weeks and
weeks you know who knows who knows I
mean that's a very open question yeah
you know there's that there's a story I
think it's Jamie we like telling this
story of you know tribal gatherings when
it the big decision needs to be made by
the tribe then you know they they put
themselves in a big tent and they're
there for as long as it takes if it
takes five minutes great if it takes six
weeks great but it takes as long as it
takes for them to actually hash it all
out and get to get to a place that
they're all happy with the commitment is
a commitment to do that right however
long it takes whatever hard it is it's
the commitment to do that which is which
is actually the important thing yeah it
was it the equation east of the the
grandmothers and east of the longhouses
so all the tribes used to get together
the thickness by trisomy the coronation
and the used to thought I'd get together
in these long houses where everything
was all the weapons were left at the
door and it was the grandmothers we used
to go to you know so maybe we should
just fine clumsy grannies all over the
world stop collected them together and
then given them a space to play out
whether you can actually care for the
people who may be falling through the
cracks and that you know I mean and then
the people who are falling through the
cracks they might not turn out to be the
hoarders
if they've got somebody to actually give
a shit about them you know I mean ya
know grace is great what about the kids
while we you know why is more of an
effort not made to include kids in these
kinds of conversations if you want to
have original ideas your honor me then
it's cute they're not encumbered by this
is how we do shit right there much much
freer to be original in there and
creative in their thinking
violence communication which was because
my Soundgarden
we're nonviolent communication is like
the key principle and it's really
amazing to see what even in three four
years old can do if they are instructed
properly how to communicate with each
other the solutions to come fix they
come up with it's just amazing and it's
throwing us out really like I like all
the adults and the politicians and
everyone else just look how it's done
just added just cuz I'm super curious
worried or where do you live mascius
Poland Poland okay and you're in the UK
Eric I I'm English so I don't live in
the UK I didn't Spain ever yes I'm
English okay cool I just wanted to know
where I'm talking to so the adjacent
possible feels like yeah you know is
creating these nodes I mean to me that's
what you know this feels like the site
was interesting as soon as I saw Jubilee
put up a
amb meeting I was like oh well I should
definitely get involved in that one you
know I've seen I've stepped into a
couple of videos of hers and I've liked
a solution raising thing I thought that
okay this makes perfect sense some of
the things that she was working on are
less interesting to me you know they're
not really like where my passions and
focus are right now but as soon as can
be like well that's one of my passions
or focus so of course I'm gonna hop in
this and I think because game B is such
the the the beacon the game beacon
that's out there right now that's really
drawing people in
having these having the ability to make
them bigger and bigger meaning more
inclusive and perhaps you know
documenting some of the things that are
the most popular ideas that can
basically be uploaded or downloaded by
the collective as it grows you know
we're debated right so whatever it is
that starts kind of coming up those
things will just become like as you said
they just rise to the top yeah these are
just change your vocabulary ever suggest
a change to your particular e there
rather than upvote and downvote sit up
regulated and down regulation amplified
and de-emphasized or whatever because
the whole notion of voting boasting is a
form of war right for voting as a form
of warfare when you can't reach
consensus you fuck you know what I mean
it's it's a failure to agree on basic
principles I think voting right you know
and and and I do think there are basic
principles on which all but a very very
very few do agree you know as we
discussed earlier so yeah no I wasn't
trying to be critical it's just this
this it's that gates is example of game
a code right that is just so automatic
that I'm sure I do it lots of times
myself but when I notice it I like to
just pick it up because it's a it's an
opportunity to reprogram ourselves a
little bit you know what I mean yeah I'm
um I've read a lot of poetry I'm a huge
fan of words and definitions which was
another thing that really drew me into
the language and clearly the brain stuff
so thanks for actually updating me on
that and
I'm really appreciate that because
language is important and shared shared
definitions are even more important than
that I think I like the ambiguous miss
and just being able just space between
the words as a guy I talk with
frequently called Ben he's he's the same
as that Kari he's exactly the same he
doesn't he gets kind of annoyed at me
sometimes I hang on a minute what do you
mean by that
yeah p.m. you know duality yeah yeah I'm
really sorry I'm just gonna jump in
again with a notion I've been developing
for a while namely that of the dance
right because life the complexity of
life requires that you juggle and
balance a whole bunch of things all the
time right and the only way to well the
best way I think to conceptualize the
doing of that is a dance because the
glass never ends right you're always
learning you're always improving and
refining the doctor elegance and it's in
its presence in the moment and
abandonment it's all of those things
brought together in one in one vessel
right there the notion and so the
religion that isn't a religion or my
religion that isn't a religion is a
commitment to being a better dancer
right learning always to try and be a
little bit better dancer than I was
yesterday sort of yeah something
something about the language and the way
we speak and what we say again because
of the children when I started to listen
listen what exactly being said I was
really surprised to discover dominant
patterns from the past from my parents
from grandparents they all just
subconsciously move and my conclusion
was we are the first generation that
actually look into this kind of thing
and we are the first generation to be
able to stop some patterns from
repeating themselves in the language oh
oh I don't know if we're the first I've
been drinking ayahuasca for about seven
years now and there are definitely you
know inherited patterns that we have in
our FP family um you know to be able to
break some of those less than beneficial
patterns is kind of a key piece to you
know psychological and emotional
well-being on a lot of levels you know
some of them they're some of the
patterns are beautiful but you know at
least that's what we at least recognize
what they are where they come from is
like a really key element and you know I
love this the notion of sovereignty and
knowing all of your you know your biases
and your tendencies and what isn't yours
things that come from society in
marketing and you know maybe incorrect
thought in your family history too but
you know there's all these kind of
pieces and like the I don't remember the
term the the unn looked at life it's not
that it's not unlooked at the unlikely
look times unexamined the unexamined
life is not worth living on so yeah oh
if we're doing quotes
something master I meant to say it
earlier but when Matthews was talking
about the basically resource-based
economic is a good I was thinking about
a quote from Jacque fresco where he said
if there's a problem in the world and
you can't make a profit from solving it
then that problem will remain unsolved
yeah yeah pretty nicely pretty nicely I
would take it one step further even
worse if there is money to be made by
creating problems in the world then
people will create those problems you
know when you look at marketing and
advertisement industry they do create
problems yeah obsolescence is basically
creating problems for consumers so there
is not a chance that some equipment
actually works for longer than the
warranty said sure yeah craziness
yeah I saw this German guy comment but
what his name is YouTube guy and he was
talking about exactly this there's this
obsolescence it's everywhere new suits
he was talking about printer cartridges
he's saying I the printer says there's
no ink left in the cartridge but built
into the cartridge this little tiny
counsel right and then when the counsel
reaches a thousand or whatever it says
the cartridge is empty but it's not at
all you reset the counter you can reset
the counsel like two three sometimes
four times and the cartridge will
continue to work so you know it's
telling you to dispose of and it's not
one where you can refill the ink rise a
disposable anyway so yeah it built built
in at every level wasting resources in
order to get yeah yeah absolutely me to
quite right good man for saying so yeah
any any other the only adjacent
Possible's I can think of that are sort
of doable and of value taking a sport is
community type experiments right that
sort of level getting 50 people together
whatever and try and create a community
on which you can rely not only for the
material necessities of life but also
for your you know social spirit
emotional needs as well right and and
figure out how to make that work because
communities break down all the time and
this has been tried many many many times
in most communities break apart right
because people simply can't get on with
each other in close proximity for long
periods of time and so figuring out a
framework in which people can do that
and not just select groups that are
perfectly blended right but that broadly
speaking groups can do that I think that
is the most important adjacent possible
sort of thing we could be doing here
here's that here's the thing about
community is that really to have let's
just say there was only a hundred people
on the planet what would you need in for
those hundred people to have kind of the
best you know technological and
emotionally balanced and fed and safe
people you know you would need you know
some measure of engineers and some
builders and some gardeners and you know
some educators and some maybe some
artists you know maybe don't need the
artists but you know that you ideally
you want you have to do you need Beauty
in your world so I don't think you
should structure it in like oh well this
person also believes and looks at the
wound averse just the way I do so I'm
gonna surround myself with that what you
actually need to look at is to structure
your communities having all of the
necessary tools within it you know
yeah that's certainly one level that's
certainly one level but conflict
resolution you know is a is a key thing
I mean you're absolutely right balancing
there balancing the skill sets is
obviously crucial that that's a step
number one almost you know what I mean
and yeah think of figuring out ways in
which because conflicts will arise right
either to try and pretend that you're
all gonna get on perfectly all the time
this is just nonsense right conflicts
will arise they're going to arise all
the time in all kinds of different ways
and so building in that like we are
always on the lookout not for not not to
conflict so that we can diffuse it but
conflict so that we can turn their
energy
into something constructive you know
what I mean like friction if you're a
fit if you've got any sort of physics
you understand that friction is what
creates for motion right it's when the
rubber hits the road it's the friction
which pushes the vehicle forward right
and so you need that you need that
friction but you you can't have it just
dissipate as heat
you know people shouting at each other
you need sir you need to channel it into
motion right into into actual
constructive forward motion and and
figuring out how to do that that seems
to me to be a but I think you can only
really do that by experimenting in good
faith and finding people willing to yeah
gauging those sorts of experiments most
people are closed lots of people of
goodwill that fails and rivalry that's
that's like it yeah very well to have a
concept that's ER to live it when people
are pissing you off you know what I mean
it's a different thing
no it's challenging but for sure we've
got about two minutes left
I mean listen I'm not thinking about the
time we can talk for as long as we want
I don't know how thingy Jubilees gonna
be about the time you know planning on
bringing us all together to maybe mix up
a little bit I don't I don't know what
her plan is I'm sorry I arrived a little
bit late so we didn't have a chance to
talk beforehand so about the voting and
the word and what voting is at least to
me and generally well 14 us as you have
a split in the whatever community and
the voting is like a final decision
people vote and then it's either this
way or that way and some part of it is
the group is going to be less happy and
the other is going to be more happy but
it's very binary the choices can be and
usually are on purpose sometimes even in
politics so well divide and conquer
right change in the language and
switching from the
all that so some things that amplified
and some things that allowed but right
downregulated ya de-emphasize do ya go
on the leaves the field still open to
evil majority wants to go this way
that's perfect but the door is not
closed for the other other direction so
yeah the problem with democracy in
general for me is that there is whenever
a choice is made is everyone is supposed
to follow and in some cases it makes
sense if you are talking about I know
cream you know something like that but
if you are talking about some soft
subjects then worry not majority it
wants to go this way surely of course
but if minority wants to do some other
things why not
so amplification and the emphasizing it
makes a huge change in how people can
think about this oh yeah so how do you
how do you you know let's just say
there's like a bunch of you know just
using your example there's a bunch of
people that are white nationalists you
know man they're really I think it's
overblown here in the United States like
yes there's some race issues you know
this is obviously highly disputed I'm a
progressive leftist in general but I
think that even the left right now is
going a little bit overboard and the the
language that is being used is being
intentionally focused into a really
tight narrow area of of pure white
racism which you know Trump is kind of
embodying and there's some elements and
you know I'm kind of a little bit off on
tangent here but how do you
for example honor people's right to be
you know believe that that the white
race is better than other races you know
what do you do
say like well you've got to live in
Arkansas you know maybe freeze believe
whatever they want if people want to
believe in case they go ahead and
believe that what they can't do is
oppress people who are not white right
but if they want to live in the
community with other white people and
sing songs about how much better white
people are than everybody else is right
if that's their thing let it be their
thing so they're not actually pressing
any to me neither there's the line comes
when those white supremacists actually
have the power to influence the way that
other people who are not them the way
that their lives go right that's that's
where the problem lies it's not in the
beliefs it's and the actions that they
can take in the world the problem and of
course we do have it in Poland like
traditionally because obviously our
nation is the best and that's every
other nation but there's like terms of
racism which is not even grounded in any
you know most of the racist here just
never had any contact with like people
of color and they still hate them
because they don't know them which kind
of works and I I switch from thinking
that well freedom of speech obviously
it's it's very important and as long as
they just say that the white rice is
supreme and stuff like that they should
be I mean there's no way to forbid them
from thinking it and we don't want to
control and I think of course but the
what I'm trying to say is the path from
just singing songs and thinking whatever
they think so actually attacking
violence on other people it's it's not a
straightforward
because even some things that are being
said in public space by politicians and
some people who are not even white
supremacists but they just think yeah
they held out views which are even not
really racist but subconsciously kind of
we are better and there is something
about publicly speaking and being in
public space which is not violence it's
not just by being that the balance is
tipped towards possibility of violent
future to describe it but edit this is a
problem because as long as much as I'm
happy for people to think whatever they
want it's obvious to me that the freedom
of what you say and how you behave I'd
really like consequences on others and I
think if you can just be mindful about
what you say you may believe in
something but if you want to be like
yeah well I'm gonna say this because
I've got free speech and I really don't
give a shit do you get yes in the
process but I think you've gotta be
mindful about what you say and who you
say to and now you say it because yeah
yeah your actions and your words can
actually have consequences and that
although other people you know I mean so
I think you've got to think of how maybe
with this what I'm sayin now would that
might affect somebody else and then
maybe I would think about that to
yourself
um and then so I choose not to sort of
like you know but as I said I just think
it's like well I'm free to say what I
like so I'll just say what I like like
Jordan Peterson carries sounds just like
Jordan Peterson on right he's right yeah
well because he would say that the
freedom of speech comes along with a
responsibility to speak
truthfully right and to speak honorably
and you cannot decouple these two things
from each other they are two sides of
the same coin
you're free to speak is my
responsibility to afford you space in
which to sense your honor man but it is
also your responsibility not to waste my
time and others with stupid speech Jenny
no I'm truthful speech with country
speech then you cannot decouple the
freedom from the responsibility the
salient we become irresponsible with
free speech and you weaponize it so use
it as I can say whatever the fuck I want
because of free speech right weaponize
it in that way then you bring people
from the other side say hang on a minute
you can't say that that's not what free
speech was intended for that's just
malicious and now you have people
questioning whether there should be free
speech because being not exposing their
responsibility to use it wisely right
and so the thing creates itself you know
I think I think that's what I was trying
to save up wanting to say it probably
ended up with one of the one of the
things I've written so far you know in
in this first kind of chapter and a half
of this book I'm writing is you know one
of the characters is a 16 year old kid
living with his family and you know he
goes through basically seven initiations
until he's considered a full adult
that's allowed to you know be a part of
the world community the greater world
community and it's kind of this evolving
network of groups so first it's his
family and then you know you start
interacting there's neighbors you have
to have all there's kind of rules and
responsibilities you know guidelines and
responsibilities and ways to you know
methods of Education that make them a
more holistic minded person as they get
older so one of the stages at you know
I'm I think I'm calling it the fifth
initiation that you go through is that
you actually spend two years abroad and
you it's in four locations you get to
pick two of them and then your parents
get to pick two of them recently just
yesterday the day before I've heard
exactly the idea somewhere else where
in the collective weird it's so weird
that you've come up with this entirely
independently it's so weird
that's the thing it's like I'm has come
all you know and I've been frustrated by
this before I'll come up with some time
like oh my god I'm gonna do this and
I'll start looking around it's like well
someone just did it like collaboration
tools and trying to put together
something and the number 7 keeps coming
up what's like so I mean you know
there's the chakras and within the wound
averse and then there's you know I mean
that I can't know there's the different
developmental stages that Ken Wilber
talks about as well and actually he has
but I'm taking the top one off because
it is actually the most considered the
most woo of the stages so I'm kind of
Allah would it just be like something
that perhaps comes after those at that
seventh stage of development and we
don't know what it is yet because of
course none of us really know when what
the truth is in terms of the whoo right
so anyway we don't know is because it's
manipulation most of the time because by
definition and work this notion that you
can only know the higher spirit to which
you are equal sometimes and what it
means is it's not even about knowledge
is about ability to recognize and
perceive stuff only that you your cause
and mind construction is actually able
to so the knowledge and being becomes
one and yeah I'm not really upset but
yeah we cannot if we were able to know
the rule
we'll be the whoo our selves I tend to
believe which is that actually there's
nothing really super natural like yes
there may indeed be something that will
once we figure it out whether it's
science or some kind of intuitive arts
and stuff it's no longer supernatural I
mean just look around the world this is
pretty magical no matter how you look at
it so it's advanced technology is
indistinguishable from magic
I need to go I've got stuff to do I've
got another call in a while and I I
personally need to go
I'm Jubilee I know is is waiting for us
to sort of wrap up Sochi and also can I
invite all of you I've really enjoyed
chatting with you can I invite all of
you there's a regular Tuesday call 8:15
p.m. UK time whatever that is and if you
give me just a minute I'll post a link
to it in the chat just just give me one
more time to chat I wanna chat here
about the what we spoke about and we've
got time to do that today object one
another time I could but much later
I need a break you know I mean if you
just message me yeah there's only one UK
time no there's there's the usual one
hour change but that's not until